Okay, hello everyone, and welcome to lecture 12.
좋습니다. 여러분 안녕하세요. 12번째 강의에 오신 것을 환영합니다.
In this lecture, we discuss optimized training of large language models.
이번 강의에서는 대규모 언어 모델의 최적화된 학습에 대해 논의합니다.
In this part, I will be presenting the part related to maximizing the GPU utilization
이번편에서는 GPU 활용도 극대화와 관련된 부분을 소개해드리겠습니다.
for efficient and scalable training.
효율적이고 확장 가능한 교육을 위한 것입니다.
Now why are we doing this?
이제 우리는 왜 이런 일을 하고 있는 걸까요?
Well, first of all, we're still seeing a lot of improvements with training bigger models,
우선, 더 큰 모델을 훈련시키면서 여전히 많은 개선이 이루어지고 있습니다.
bigger language models.
더 큰 언어 모델.
And as of right now, current GPUs cannot train more than 1.4 billion parameters in one GPU.
그리고 현재로서는 현재 GPU는 하나의 GPU에서 14억 개가 넘는 매개변수를 훈련할 수 없습니다.
So how do we achieve bigger models on multiple GPUs?
그렇다면 여러 GPU에서 더 큰 모델을 어떻게 달성할 수 있을까요?
How can we divide them?
어떻게 나눌 수 있나요?
And this is going to be the main topic of this presentation today.
이것이 오늘 프레젠테이션의 주요 주제가 될 것입니다.
We cannot just throw a lot of GPUs at the problem and think that it's going to be solved.
우리는 문제에 많은 GPU를 투입하고 문제가 해결될 것이라고 생각할 수 없습니다.
Hopefully, after this presentation, you will appreciate the engineering put into it.
이 프레젠테이션을 마친 후에는 여기에 적용된 엔지니어링에 대해 감사하게 될 것입니다.
So a little bit of an ambitious outline here, but we're going to be talking about parallelism
여기에는 약간의 야심찬 개요가 있지만 병렬성에 대해 이야기하겠습니다.
primitives.
기초 요소.
So we're going to be talking about data parallelism, pipeline parallelism, model parallelism,
그래서 우리는 데이터 병렬성, 파이프라인 병렬성, 모델 병렬성,
and then finally the zero optimizer.
그리고 마지막으로 제로 옵티마이저입니다.
And we're going to be also talking about some necessary optimizations for these things
그리고 우리는 이러한 것들에 필요한 몇 가지 최적화에 대해서도 이야기할 것입니다.
to work, like activation checkpointing and mixed precision training.
활성화 체크포인트 및 혼합 정밀 훈련과 같은 작업을 수행합니다.
So first, let's just talk about data parallelism.
먼저, 데이터 병렬성에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
What is data parallelism?
데이터 병렬성이란 무엇입니까?
Data parallelism is the first straightforward implementation of some form of parallelism over
데이터 병렬화는 데이터 병렬화의 일부 형태를 최초로 직접적으로 구현한 것입니다.
multiple GPUs.
다중 GPU.
So the idea is, given a mini-batch, you distribute it over multiple, so you split the mini-batch
따라서 아이디어는 미니 배치가 주어지면 여러 개로 배포하여 미니 배치를 분할하는 것입니다.
into multiple micro-batches for every GPU.
모든 GPU에 대해 여러 개의 마이크로 배치로 구성됩니다.
And basically, every GPU has a copy of the model.
그리고 기본적으로 모든 GPU에는 모델의 복사본이 있습니다.
Now every GPU does a forward pass, backward pass, computes the gradients, and then they
이제 모든 GPU는 순방향 패스, 역방향 패스를 수행하고 기울기를 계산한 다음
can aggregate these gradients together, either using a parameter server, could be another
매개변수 서버를 사용하여 이러한 그라데이션을 함께 집계할 수 있습니다.
GPU, or they do some form of old reduce operation.
GPU이거나 어떤 형태의 오래된 축소 작업을 수행합니다.
And by this way, they reduce all the gradients together, and then they broadcast the updated
이런 방식으로 그들은 모든 경사도를 함께 줄인 다음 업데이트된 내용을 방송합니다.
model to all of them, and then they go on to the next mini-batch.
그들 모두에게 모델을 적용한 후 다음 미니 배치로 넘어갑니다.
The good thing about this is that you get immediately, so for these three GPUs, you
이것의 좋은 점은 즉시 얻을 수 있다는 것입니다. 따라서 이 세 가지 GPU의 경우
get three extra throughput.
3개의 추가 처리량을 얻습니다.
And there is no design that you need to do.
그리고 꼭 해야 할 디자인도 없습니다.
Enter pipeline parallelism.
파이프라인 병렬 처리를 시작하세요.
It was introduced in GPype and PyveDream, and the idea is, instead of having the model
GPype 및 PyveDream에 도입되었으며 아이디어는 모델을 갖는 대신
copied in every GPU, you have an interlayer splitting.
모든 GPU에 복사되면 레이어 간 분할이 발생합니다.
So you split the model, so the first layer isn't the first GPU, the second layer isn't
따라서 모델을 분할하면 첫 번째 레이어는 첫 번째 GPU가 아니고 두 번째 레이어는 GPU가 아닙니다.
the second GPU, the third layer isn't the third GPU, and so on.
두 번째 GPU, 세 번째 레이어는 세 번째 GPU가 아닙니다.
And so hopefully, every layer will have one over the number of devices of the weights,
그리고 바라건대, 모든 레이어에는 가중치 장치 수만큼의 장치가 있을 것입니다.
so it will have less memory, and you just pass the mini-batch, you split it into also
따라서 메모리가 더 적으므로 미니 배치를 전달하고 이를 다음과 같이 분할합니다.
three micro-batches, and you pass them in sequence in a pipeline.
3개의 마이크로 배치를 파이프라인에서 순서대로 전달합니다.
But the naive way to do this will not work, because if you just make the forward through
하지만 이렇게 하는 순진한 방법은 효과가 없습니다. 왜냐하면 단지 앞으로 나아가면 되기 때문입니다.
the first layer, then the forward, the second layer, third layer, fourth layer, and then
첫 번째 레이어, 그 다음 앞으로, 두 번째 레이어, 세 번째 레이어, 네 번째 레이어, 그리고
you go backward in each of them, basically you're having the performance of one GPU,
각각을 거꾸로 보면 기본적으로 하나의 GPU 성능을 갖게 됩니다.
and all of the white blocks here are idle, or bubbles.
여기 있는 흰색 블록은 모두 유휴 상태이거나 거품입니다.
So how can we optimize that?
그러면 어떻게 최적화할 수 있을까요?
Well, this is the idea behind GPype.
글쎄, 이것이 GPype의 아이디어입니다.
The idea is while the first batch does forward, then after that, the next batch goes in, like
아이디어는 첫 번째 배치가 진행되는 동안 그 후 다음 배치가 시작된다는 것입니다.
in a pipeline way, and then the third batch goes in, and then the fourth batch, and the
파이프라인 방식으로 세 번째 배치가 들어가고 네 번째 배치가 들어가고
idea is that we want to maximize the number of these full-length columns, because at these
아이디어는 우리가 이러한 전체 길이 열의 수를 최대화하고 싶다는 것입니다.
full-length columns is when the pipeline is completely utilized, and this is the maximum
전체 길이 열은 파이프라인을 완전히 활용한 경우이며 이는 최대입니다.
utilization that we want.
우리가 원하는 활용.
So this is an extensive example of this idea in motion.
이것은 이 아이디어가 실행되는 광범위한 예입니다.
So we have eight micro-batches.
그래서 우리는 8개의 마이크로 배치를 갖게 되었습니다.
We will interleave them forward and backward in the following way.
다음과 같은 방법으로 앞뒤로 인터리브할 것입니다.
So the moment the first batch finishes, the second batch goes on, and so on.
따라서 첫 번째 배치가 끝나는 순간 두 번째 배치가 계속됩니다.
So for the first layer, second layer, third layer, fourth layer, and then you do the backwards
따라서 첫 번째 레이어, 두 번째 레이어, 세 번째 레이어, 네 번째 레이어에 대해 그런 다음 거꾸로 수행합니다.
for each of them, and essentially this is what you have.
각각에 대해 본질적으로 이것이 당신이 가지고 있는 것입니다.
You have more full-length columns, and so you have higher throughput and more utilization.
전체 길이 열이 더 많아 처리량과 활용도가 더 높아집니다.
If we want to analyze this more firmly, we look at the bubble time per mini-batch.
이를 좀 더 확실하게 분석하고 싶다면 미니 배치당 버블 시간을 살펴보겠습니다.
So the bubble time is the number of devices minus one times the forward plus backward
따라서 버블 시간은 장치 수에서 앞으로 + 뒤로 + 1을 뺀 값입니다.
time, which is essentially the time that it takes for a mini-batch to fully enter through
시간은 본질적으로 미니 배치가 완전히 진입하는 데 걸리는 시간입니다.
the pipeline and to fully withdraw.
파이프라인을 완전히 철수합니다.
Ideally, we want to be using, so m here is the number of micro-batches, so we want the
이상적으로 우리는 다음을 사용하고 싶습니다. 여기서 m은 마이크로 배치의 수이므로 우리는
ideal time is to be m times tf plus tb.
이상적인 시간은 m 곱하기 tf + tb 입니다.
So the efficiency that we get out of that is, well, if you do the calculation, it's
그래서 우리가 얻는 효율성은, 음, 계산을 하면,
one minus k minus one over m.
1 빼기 k 빼기 1 나누기 m.
And in GPype, they find that empirically for almost linear scaling, you need the number
그리고 GPype에서는 경험적으로 거의 선형적인 스케일링을 위해서는 다음 숫자가 필요하다는 것을 알았습니다.
of micro-batches to be bigger than or equal four times the number of devices.
마이크로 배치의 수는 장치 수의 4배 이상이어야 합니다.
And if you plug in this in our analysis here, we get that it's effectively 75 percent scaling
여기 분석에 이를 연결하면 사실상 75% 확장이 가능하다는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
efficiency, which is good enough.
효율성은 충분합니다.
And if you increase m more than that, well, you get higher efficiency.
그리고 m을 그 이상으로 늘리면 효율성이 높아집니다.
And well, pipeline parallelism reduces the memory proportional to the number of pipeline
그리고 파이프라인 병렬화는 파이프라인 수에 비례하여 메모리를 줄입니다.
stages.
단계.
So it allows the model size to scale linearly with the number of workers, and it has the
따라서 모델 크기가 작업자 수에 따라 선형적으로 확장될 수 있으며,
lowest communication volume.
최저 통신량.
However, it cannot scale indefinitely, because increasing the pipeline size decreases the
그러나 파이프라인 크기를 늘리면 파이프라인이 줄어들기 때문에 무한정 확장할 수는 없습니다.
computation per pipeline stage.
파이프라인 단계당 계산.
And it needs loads balancing.
그리고 로드 밸런싱이 필요합니다.
It is architecture independent, but it does need a little bit of code rewriting.
아키텍처 독립적이지만 약간의 코드 재작성이 필요합니다.
And the memory pair device, it's got to be the maximum partition, so like the maximum
그리고 메모리 쌍 장치는 최대 파티션이어야 합니다.
width of layer, plus the activations for all the micro-batches, because they are stored
레이어 너비와 모든 마이크로 배치에 대한 활성화가 저장되기 때문입니다.
as we are going.
우리가 가는 대로.
Enter the next parallelism idea, which is to split it the other way.
다른 방식으로 분할하는 다음 병렬 처리 아이디어를 입력합니다.
Instead of splitting it layer by layer, you split the layer itself horizontally.
레이어별로 분할하는 대신 레이어 자체를 가로로 분할합니다.
So we split this first layer here, we split these two things, we split them, and so on.
그래서 우리는 여기서 첫 번째 레이어를 분할하고, 이 두 가지를 분할하고, 분할하는 식으로 진행합니다.
And the idea is that we're computing every layer in parallel.
그리고 아이디어는 우리가 모든 레이어를 병렬로 계산한다는 것입니다.
And since this really requires us to go into the depth of implementation of these blocks,
그리고 이를 위해서는 실제로 이러한 블록을 구현하는 방법을 자세히 살펴보아야 하므로,
we're only going to be focusing on the transformer block, which is exactly what the paper megatron
우리는 종이 메가트론과 정확히 같은 트랜스포머 블록에만 초점을 맞출 것입니다.
did.
했다.
So what is the main component in training large language models?
그렇다면 대규모 언어 모델을 훈련하는 데 있어 주요 구성 요소는 무엇입니까?
It's basically matrix multiplication.
기본적으로 행렬 곱셈입니다.
So we are focusing on generalized matrix multiplication here.
그래서 우리는 여기서 일반화된 행렬 곱셈에 초점을 맞추고 있습니다.
And in the paper, they introduce two forms of parallelism.
그리고 논문에서는 두 가지 형태의 병렬성을 소개합니다.
In column parallelism, so you're multiplying x times a, and you want to do this on two
열 병렬 처리에서는 x 곱하기 a를 곱하고 이를 2번에 수행하려고 합니다.
devices.
장치.
So what you do is you split a by column, so you put the first column here, and you put
그래서 당신이 하는 일은 열을 기준으로 나누는 것입니다. 따라서 여기에 첫 번째 열을 놓고
the second column here, and then you replicate x on both devices, and then you do the multiplication.
여기에 두 번째 열을 입력하고 두 장치 모두에서 x를 복제한 다음 곱셈을 수행합니다.
Now when you do the multiplication, this output is going to be the first column of the output,
이제 곱셈을 하면 이 출력이 출력의 첫 번째 열이 됩니다.
and this output is going to be the second column of the output, and you just want concatenate
이 출력은 출력의 두 번째 열이 될 것이며 연결만 하면 됩니다.
them.
그들을.
For row parallelism, however, instead of splitting a by column, you split it by rows.
그러나 행 병렬 처리의 경우 열을 기준으로 분할하는 대신 행을 기준으로 분할합니다.
So you send the top to the first device, and the bottom to the second device, and you also
따라서 상단을 첫 번째 장치로 보내고 하단을 두 번째 장치로 보냅니다.
split x by column this time.
이번에는 x를 열로 나눕니다.
So you put the left side on the first device, and the right side on the second device.
따라서 왼쪽을 첫 번째 장치에 놓고 오른쪽을 두 번째 장치에 놓습니다.
And when you do the multiplication, now the output is going to be a partial sum of the
그리고 곱셈을 하면 이제 출력은 다음의 부분 합이 됩니다.
final output.
최종 출력.
So it's like this entry should be all of this times all of this.
따라서 이 항목은 이 모든 시간의 모든 시간이 되어야 하는 것과 같습니다.
The first device is going to be computing this times this.
첫 번째 장치는 이번 시간에 컴퓨팅을 수행하게 됩니다.
So it's going to be here, x11, x12, a11, a21.
그래서 그것은 여기 x11, x12, a11, a21이 될 것입니다.
When you multiply this and this, you get y1 of 1, 1.
이것과 이것을 곱하면 y1/1, 1이 됩니다.
In order to get the rest of it, the second device needs to compute this times this, which
나머지를 얻으려면 두 번째 장치가 이 시간을 계산해야 합니다.
is going to be here, then the output is going to be here.
여기에 있을 것이고 출력은 여기에 있을 것입니다.
The idea here, the costly thing you need to do is you need to sum these up.
여기서 아이디어는 비용이 많이 드는 작업을 요약해야 한다는 것입니다.
And summing across devices means that there is some form of communication that needs to
그리고 여러 장치에 걸쳐 합산한다는 것은 다음과 같은 형태의 통신이 필요하다는 것을 의미합니다.
happen.
일어나다.
Concatenation, you can do the concatenation logically.
연결, 논리적으로 연결을 수행할 수 있습니다.
There doesn't have to be communication between them.
그들 사이에 의사소통이 있을 필요는 없습니다.
You can just think of the tensor as existing into machines but being split.
텐서는 기계에 존재하지만 분할되는 것으로 생각할 수 있습니다.
While here, you cannot think of it like that.
여기에 있는 동안에는 그런 생각을 할 수 없습니다.
You have to add them.
당신은 그들을 추가해야합니다.
So how does this apply into the transformer?
그렇다면 이것이 변압기에 어떻게 적용됩니까?
The idea can apply to the self-attention block except that we basically will parallelize
이 아이디어는 기본적으로 병렬화한다는 점을 제외하면 self-attention 블록에 적용될 수 있습니다.
attention heads now.
지금 주목하세요.
So let's assume, for the sake of example, that we have only two attention heads.
예를 들어 주의 헤드가 두 개만 있다고 가정해 보겠습니다.
We're going to put every attention head on a separate device.
우리는 모든 주의를 별도의 장치에 집중시킬 것입니다.
So the first device is going to take, again, column parallelism.
따라서 첫 번째 장치는 다시 열 병렬성을 사용하게 됩니다.
We're going to take x and we're going to split the v, q, and k by column.
x를 선택하고 v, q, k를 열별로 분할하겠습니다.
And then we are going to do the attention and then we use the row parallelism in order
그런 다음 주의를 기울이고 행 병렬성을 순서대로 사용합니다.
to complete the linear layer at the end of the self-attention.
self-attention이 끝나면 선형 레이어를 완성합니다.
That's basically it.
기본적으로 그게 다입니다.
That's how you parallelize a transformer block horizontally.
이것이 변압기 블록을 수평으로 병렬화하는 방법입니다.
In summary, basically you have two all-reduced operations, one for forward and one for backward
요약하면 기본적으로 두 개의 전체 축소 작업이 있습니다. 하나는 순방향, 다른 하나는 역방향입니다.
for the attention block, and you have the same thing for the model parallel blocks
어텐션 블록의 경우 모델 병렬 블록의 경우에도 동일합니다.
that they are in total for all-reduced operations, which is a lot.
전체적으로 축소된 작업을 수행하기 위한 것인데, 이는 많은 양입니다.
So this idea of parallelism is essentially very expensive in terms of communication cost.
따라서 병렬성에 대한 아이디어는 본질적으로 통신 비용 측면에서 매우 비쌉니다.
So the results of that from the paper is that, well, you can, first of all, you can compose
따라서 논문의 결과는 음, 무엇보다도 먼저 다음을 작성할 수 있다는 것입니다.
it with data parallelism.
데이터 병렬성을 사용합니다.
So model parallel on its own has like 77% scaling efficiency.
따라서 모델 병렬 자체의 확장 효율성은 77% 정도입니다.
So at 8 GPUs, instead of getting 8x the performance, you get 77% times 8x of the performance.
따라서 8개의 GPU에서는 8배의 성능을 얻는 대신 77% x 8배의 성능을 얻습니다.
And if you combine that with data parallel, you get 74% at 512 of GPUs, which is like
그리고 이를 데이터 병렬과 결합하면 512개의 GPU에서 74%를 얻게 됩니다.
a lot.
많이.
And that gives you basically a very high throughput that you can use for training larger and larger
그리고 이는 기본적으로 점점 더 큰 규모의 훈련에 사용할 수 있는 매우 높은 처리량을 제공합니다.
language models.
언어 모델.
But as we said, it's the highest communication volume, but it has the highest memory efficiency
하지만 우리가 말했듯이 통신량이 가장 높지만 메모리 효율성도 가장 높습니다.
because we really split the computation across devices.
우리는 실제로 계산을 여러 장치에 걸쳐 분할하기 때문입니다.
However, it reduces the granularity of the computation while also increasing the communication
그러나 이는 계산의 세분성을 감소시키는 동시에 통신을 증가시킵니다.
overhead, which makes it not very good in cases where it would be across multiple devices.
오버헤드가 발생하므로 여러 장치에 걸쳐 있는 경우에는 그다지 좋지 않습니다.
So if you were using GPUs from multiple devices, there becomes a communication bottleneck.
따라서 여러 장치에서 GPU를 사용하는 경우 통신 병목 현상이 발생합니다.
So usually we just use model parallelism on GPUs inside the same like node or server,
그래서 일반적으로 우리는 노드나 서버와 같은 내부의 GPU에서 모델 병렬성을 사용합니다.
for example.
예를 들어.
Other details is that it actually parallelizes the embedding layer and the loss layer.
다른 세부 사항은 임베딩 레이어와 손실 레이어를 실제로 병렬화한다는 것입니다.
And the idea is the same, basically, we use the parallel GMM and masking.
그리고 아이디어는 동일합니다. 기본적으로 우리는 병렬 GMM과 마스킹을 사용합니다.
And because it is bad across internal GPUs, to scale higher, we use data parallel or model
그리고 내부 GPU 전체에서는 좋지 않기 때문에 더 높은 수준으로 확장하기 위해 데이터 병렬 또는 모델을 사용합니다.
pipelining, like we compose it with other parallelism parameters.
다른 병렬성 매개변수로 구성하는 것처럼 파이프라이닝합니다.
So in summary, we can split the data and not the model.
요약하자면, 모델이 아닌 데이터를 분할할 수 있습니다.
We can just send the data to multiple devices and keep the model existing on every device
데이터를 여러 장치로 전송하고 모든 장치에 모델이 존재하도록 유지할 수 있습니다.
and do the training that is very fast.
그리고 아주 빠른 훈련을 하세요.
We can split the model horizontally, so every layer is a split, and we can give it the whole
모델을 수평으로 분할할 수 있으므로 모든 레이어가 분할되어 전체를 제공할 수 있습니다.
batch at once.
한 번에 일괄 처리합니다.
That is very communication intensive, but the lowest memory footprint.
이는 매우 통신 집약적이지만 메모리 사용량은 가장 낮습니다.
And we can split it vertically like this and feed the batches to it sequentially.
그리고 우리는 이것을 이렇게 수직으로 분할하고 배치를 순차적으로 공급할 수 있습니다.
And that is the highest memory efficiency, that is also very high memory efficiency and
그리고 그것은 최고의 메모리 효율성이며, 또한 매우 높은 메모리 효율성입니다.
the lowest communication bottleneck.
통신 병목 현상이 가장 낮습니다.
So can we combine them together?
그럼 그것들을 함께 결합할 수 있을까요?
Can we get the best of three worlds in that case?
이 경우 세 가지 세계 중 가장 좋은 점을 얻을 수 있습니까?
And the answer is yes, actually.
대답은 '예'입니다.
You can think of each of these as a device and you can abstract it and subdivide it in
이들 각각을 하나의 장치로 생각하고 추상화하여 세분화할 수 있습니다.
these ways, and this is actually what 3D parallelism is.
이것이 바로 3D 병렬성입니다.
So you take your batch and you split it into microbatches, each microbatch goes into a
따라서 배치를 가져와 마이크로배치로 나누고, 각 마이크로배치는
data parallel slice.
데이터 병렬 슬라이스.
The data parallel slice basically consists of the whole model, but the model itself is
데이터 병렬 슬라이스는 기본적으로 전체 모델로 구성되지만, 모델 자체는
split sequentially into three stages in that case.
이 경우 순차적으로 세 단계로 나눕니다.
They are pipeline parallelism blocks, like we described them earlier.
앞서 설명한 것처럼 파이프라인 병렬 처리 블록입니다.
And each one of these pipeline parallel blocks is split into, for example, two model parallel
그리고 이러한 파이프라인 병렬 블록 각각은 예를 들어 두 개의 모델 병렬로 분할됩니다.
blocks or tensor parallel blocks, such that you can have parallelism at the level of the
블록 또는 텐서 병렬 블록을 사용하여 수준에서 병렬성을 가질 수 있습니다.
tensor itself.
텐서 그 자체.
And because this is the NR level, it's good for communication purposes, and this is good
그리고 이게 NR급이라 통신용으로도 좋고, 이것도 좋아요
for efficiency purposes, and this is good for scaling purposes.
효율성을 위해 이는 확장 목적에 적합합니다.
So mixing them all together gives you the highest achievable parallelism you can get
따라서 이들을 모두 혼합하면 달성 가능한 가장 높은 병렬성을 얻을 수 있습니다.
with the current technology.
현재 기술로.
And this is actually the state of the art right now.
그리고 이것은 실제로 현재의 최첨단 기술입니다.
So this is the model for Bloom, for example.
예를 들어 이것은 Bloom의 모델입니다.
It allows, so this is like 384 GPUs.
허용하므로 이는 384 GPU와 같습니다.
It's like in sign.
마치 사인과 같습니다.
You get eight copies of the model trained on a total of 384 GPUs.
총 384개의 GPU에서 훈련된 모델의 8개 복사본을 얻습니다.
So you get eight copies.
따라서 8개의 사본을 얻게 됩니다.
This is the data parallelism.
이것이 데이터 병렬성이다.
Each copy is divided into 12 pipeline parallelism steps.
각 복사본은 12개의 파이프라인 병렬 처리 단계로 나뉩니다.
So this is the sequence of steps.
이것이 일련의 단계입니다.
And then each pipeline step is divided into four model parallel steps.
그런 다음 각 파이프라인 단계는 4개의 모델 병렬 단계로 나뉩니다.
So one full copy takes 48 GPUs times eight to get 384.
따라서 하나의 전체 복사본은 384개를 얻으려면 48개의 GPU x 8이 필요합니다.
Amazing.
놀라운.
Okay, now let's talk about mixed precision training.
자, 이제 혼합 정밀도 훈련에 대해 이야기해 보겠습니다.
Mixed precision training is basically the idea that allows us to train in smaller precision
혼합 정밀도 훈련은 기본적으로 더 작은 정밀도로 훈련할 수 있게 해주는 아이디어입니다.
than 32 bits, because 32 bits, like it's actually, this paper shows that it is not
32비트보다 32비트가 실제로 그렇듯이 이 문서에서는 그렇지 않다는 것을 보여줍니다.
necessary to train in 32 bits.
32비트로 학습하는 데 필요합니다.
You need to keep the original weights in 32 bits, because the gradient time is the learning
기울기 시간이 학습이기 때문에 원래 가중치를 32비트로 유지해야 합니다.
rate is sometimes too small, but the memory is dominated by the activations.
속도는 때로는 너무 작지만 메모리는 활성화에 의해 지배됩니다.
So it's okay to keep the original weight in 32 bits, and actually convert every single
그러니까 원래의 가중치를 32비트로 유지하고, 실제로는 모든 것을 변환해도 괜찮습니다.
thing else into 16 bits, and you will get very close accuracy.
다른 것을 16비트로 나누면 매우 가까운 정확도를 얻을 수 있습니다.
There's a couple of net picks to this, which is in FP16 a lot.
이에 대한 몇 가지 순 선택이 있는데, 이는 FP16에 많이 있습니다.
So basically part of the gradient that is here, this part is in the subnormalized range,
기본적으로 여기에 있는 그래디언트의 일부입니다. 이 부분은 정규화되지 않은 범위에 있습니다.
so it's not representable in FP16, and it becomes zero.
따라서 FP16에서는 표현할 수 없으며 0이 됩니다.
So the way you do it is actually you just scale the loss, because this is the important
그래서 당신이 하는 방식은 실제로 손실의 크기를 조정하는 것입니다. 왜냐하면 이것이 중요하기 때문입니다.
part, so you scale the loss a little bit, depending on the kind of model you're using.
부분이므로 사용하는 모델의 종류에 따라 손실을 약간 조정할 수 있습니다.
So you move this part that becomes zero in FP16 from this red line to this orange line
그래서 FP16에서 0이 되는 부분을 이 빨간색 선에서 이 주황색 선으로 이동합니다.
by scaling all the gradients, and the easiest way to scale all the gradients is to just
모든 그라디언트의 크기를 조정하고 모든 그라디언트의 크기를 조정하는 가장 쉬운 방법은
scale the loss.
손실 규모를 조정하세요.
You multiply the loss by like 2 power 4 here, and in other situations it's 2 power 8 or
여기에서는 손실에 2제곱 4를 곱하고 다른 상황에서는 2제곱 8 또는
2 power 16, depending, not 2 power 8 or 2 power 10, and you get basically essentially
2제곱 16, 2제곱 8 또는 2제곱 10이 아니라 기본적으로 기본적으로 얻습니다.
the same accuracy, so you get the same exact model as if you did it in 32 bits, and in
정확도가 동일하므로 32비트에서 수행한 것과 동일한 정확한 모델을 얻을 수 있습니다.
some situations it's actually slightly a little bit more accurate, and I think it's
어떤 상황에서는 실제로 약간 더 정확하기도 합니다.
just because like some regularization effect that happens when you're training in 16 bits,
16비트로 훈련할 때 발생하는 정규화 효과처럼
it's like the model generalizes a little bit better.
모델이 좀 더 일반화되는 것과 같습니다.
So in summary, FP16 is faster than FP32 anyway, so we prefer that, and it takes less memory.
요약하자면 FP16은 어쨌든 FP32보다 빠르므로 우리는 이를 선호하고 메모리도 덜 차지합니다.
We divide the memory by approximately 2, so that is good.
메모리를 약 2로 나누면 좋습니다.
We definitely want to incorporate that, and most of the papers that came after this paper
우리는 확실히 그것을 통합하고 싶고 이 논문 이후에 나온 대부분의 논문도
in training large-language models, they utilize this mixed precision training.
대규모 언어 모델을 훈련할 때 이러한 혼합 정밀도 훈련을 활용합니다.
We also utilize activation checkpointing, which is a very simple idea actually, so usually
우리는 또한 실제로 매우 간단한 아이디어인 활성화 체크포인트를 활용합니다.
when you're training a model you keep the forward states, so you train a model, you
모델을 훈련할 때 순방향 상태를 유지하므로 모델을 훈련하면
do forwards, you keep all the forward states with you, and then after you do the forward
전달을 수행하면 모든 전달 상태를 그대로 유지하고 전달을 수행한 후에는
you compute the loss, and when you're doing the loss you start going backward, and when
손실을 계산하고 손실이 발생하면 뒤로 가기 시작합니다.
you're going backward you compute the backward gradient from the saved state and the backward
뒤로 이동하면 저장된 상태에서 역방향 그래디언트를 계산하고 역방향
gradient that is coming, so you back propagate here, and then you go here, you get this state,
그래디언트가 다가오고 있으므로 여기서 다시 전파하고 여기로 가면 이 상태가 됩니다.
and this you go back propagate, and so on.
그리고 이것을 다시 전파하는 식입니다.
But you don't need to keep all of these states in memory, in fact you can keep only square
하지만 이 모든 상태를 메모리에 보관할 필요는 없습니다. 실제로는 정사각형만 유지할 수 있습니다.
root of them, so like you can do one and skip three, and one and skip three, and every time
예를 들어, 하나를 하고 세 개를 건너뛰고, 하나를 하고 세 개를 건너뛰고, 매번
you're doing backward you recompute from the last checkpoint, that is why it's called
거꾸로 수행하고 마지막 체크포인트에서 다시 계산하므로 호출됩니다.
checkpointing.
검문소.
So from this checkpoint it starts automatically when you start going backward, so it does
그래서 이 체크포인트부터 뒤로 가기 시작하면 자동으로 시작됩니다.
some forward for you and gives you this so that it's ready for back propagating, and
일부는 여러분을 위해 전달하고 이를 역전파할 준비가 되도록 제공합니다.
when you do that it triggers this one to start computing too, so when it starts going forward
그렇게 하면 이 항목도 컴퓨팅을 시작하게 되므로 앞으로 진행되기 시작하면
it can meet you somewhere in the middle, so you're not really waiting for it, you can
중간 어딘가에서 만날 수 있으므로 별로 기다리지 않아도 됩니다.
just spend a little bit of extra compute for the sake of reducing the memory tremendously.
메모리를 엄청나게 줄이기 위해 약간의 추가 컴퓨팅을 소비하면 됩니다.
In the case of doing it, actually every square root steps you get square root of n memory
이를 수행하는 경우 실제로 모든 제곱근 단계마다 n 메모리의 제곱근을 얻습니다.
reduction at the expense of like one extra forward per mini batch, it's like 33% of the
미니 배치당 하나의 추가 전달을 희생하여 감소하면 33% 정도입니다.
computation increase, at least in the case of a transformer, which is very, very, very,
적어도 변환기의 경우 계산 증가는 매우, 매우, 매우
very good.
매우 좋은.
Now we go to zero. Zero is zero redundancy optimizer, it is from Microsoft. It's basically
이제 우리는 0으로갑니다. Zero는 제로 중복 최적화 프로그램이며 Microsoft에서 제공합니다. 그것은 기본적으로
an optimizer that uses most of the things that we talked about so far, and it does them
지금까지 이야기한 대부분의 기능을 사용하는 최적화 프로그램입니다.
in a clever way that makes the memory consumption basically amortized to like being actually
메모리 소비를 기본적으로 상각하여 실제로 좋아하게 만드는 영리한 방법으로
divided by the number of devices, like the original memory consumption divided by the
원래 메모리 소비량을 장치 수로 나눈 것과 같습니다.
number of devices, right away like from 120 gigabytes you go down to 1.9 gigabytes, insane.
장치 수는 120GB에서 1.9GB로 즉시 줄어듭니다.
So how does it go? It goes essentially like this, so first of all how much memory does
그럼 어떻게 되나요? 본질적으로 다음과 같이 진행됩니다. 따라서 우선 얼마나 많은 메모리가
the model take? Well, it takes every parameter, it takes two bytes, like FP16, so it takes
모델 테이크? 음, 모든 매개변수를 사용합니다. FP16처럼 2바이트를 사용하므로
two bytes for the parameters, two bytes for the gradients, and then there are some optimizer
매개변수에 2바이트, 그래디언트에 2바이트, 그리고 일부 최적화 프로그램이 있습니다.
states, which because these optimizer states are like in 32 bits, they are four plus four
이러한 최적화 프로그램 상태는 32비트와 같기 때문에 4 더하기 4입니다.
bytes, so they are actually 12 here. And then you multiply it by the number of parameters,
바이트이므로 실제로는 12입니다. 그런 다음 매개변수 개수를 곱하면 됩니다.
this is what you get. So there are three levels of parallelism that zero does. The first one
이것이 당신이 얻는 것입니다. 따라서 0에는 세 가지 수준의 병렬 처리가 있습니다. 첫번째
is optimizer state parallelism, and then optimizer state plus gradient parallelism, and then
옵티마이저 상태 병렬성, 그리고 옵티마이저 상태에 그라디언트 병렬성을 더한 것입니다.
optimizer state plus gradient plus parameter parallelism. And in here, we can see the speed
최적화 상태, 그래디언트, 매개변수 병렬성. 여기서는 속도를 볼 수 있습니다.
up of zero being very high. We can see that, well, the throughput per GPU, it's like consistent,
0이 되면 매우 높습니다. GPU당 처리량은 일관적이라는 것을 알 수 있습니다.
it only starts to go down in like very high model parameters, but the speed up is really high,
매우 높은 모델 매개변수에서만 감소하기 시작하지만 속도 증가는 정말 빠릅니다.
and the speed up becomes really significant when the model can no longer fit on a single node.
모델이 더 이상 단일 노드에 적합하지 않을 때 속도 향상은 매우 중요해집니다.
So in here, the baseline is model parallelism on a single device where you can see like they
여기서 기준은 다음과 같은 것을 볼 수 있는 단일 장치에서의 모델 병렬성입니다.
are relatively close, but after this point, it can no longer fit on a single node. So you need
상대적으로 가깝지만 이 시점 이후에는 더 이상 단일 노드에 들어갈 수 없습니다. 그래서 당신은 필요합니다
to have inter node model parallelism in order to fit it. This is where the throughput per GPU
이를 맞추기 위해 노드 간 모델 병렬성을 갖습니다. GPU당 처리량은 다음과 같습니다.
goes down really fast, and this is where zero optimizer really shines because it scales so much
정말 빠르게 다운되는데, 제로 옵티마이저가 정말 빛나는 이유는 확장성이 너무 크기 때문입니다.
better in high parameter situations. Okay, so here we see an example of zero on four devices,
매개변수가 높은 상황에서는 더 좋습니다. 좋습니다. 여기서는 4개의 장치에서 0의 예를 볼 수 있습니다.
each device has a portion of the model, so device one has this portion and so on, and then in the
각 장치에는 모델의 일부가 있으므로 장치 1에는 이 부분이 있고 그 다음에는
forward batch, each party corresponding to a certain section of the model, it sends it to all
포워드 배치, 모델의 특정 섹션에 해당하는 각 당사자를 모두에게 보냅니다.
the clients so that they can do the forward on their respective data. So this is a form of data
클라이언트가 각자의 데이터를 전달할 수 있도록 합니다. 그래서 이것은 데이터의 한 형태입니다.
parallel combined with pipeline parallel. The forward then gets computed with the loss when
파이프라인 병렬과 결합된 병렬. 포워드는 다음과 같은 경우 손실로 계산됩니다.
you're doing the backward loss in your part of the data, in your part of the model, all the parties
당신은 데이터의 당신 부분, 모델의 당신 부분, 모든 당사자에서 역방향 손실을 겪고 있습니다.
give you the gradient for this part of the model. And so the communication that happens only happens
모델의 이 부분에 대한 그라데이션을 제공합니다. 그래서 일어나는 의사소통은 단지 일어난다.
when needed, and every party only carries the data that it needs. So it's kind of like a complete
필요한 경우 모든 당사자는 필요한 데이터만 전달합니다. 그러니까 완전체같아
partitioning of the model and the data at the same time. And when it's time, you update your model
모델과 데이터를 동시에 분할합니다. 그리고 때가 되면 모델을 업데이트하세요.
with your optimizer states, you get the new model parameters, and then you go for the next batch,
최적화 상태를 사용하여 새로운 모델 매개변수를 얻은 다음 다음 배치로 이동합니다.
and this is essentially the whole idea. Now you can use zero on its own as a data parallel approach
이것이 본질적으로 전체 아이디어입니다. 이제 데이터 병렬 접근 방식으로 0을 자체적으로 사용할 수 있습니다.
in 3D parallelism, and this is the deep speed library. So you can have a data parallel using zero,
3D 병렬 처리에 사용되며 이것이 깊은 속도 라이브러리입니다. 따라서 0을 사용하여 데이터 병렬을 가질 수 있습니다.
and then each data parallel inside it, there is pipeline parallel, and each pipeline parallel has
그 안에 각 데이터가 병렬로 있고 파이프라인 병렬이 있으며 각 파이프라인 병렬은
inside it model parallel. So you have the 3D parallelism with the zero optimization, which
내부 모델은 평행합니다. 따라서 최적화가 0인 3D 병렬성을 갖게 됩니다.
significantly improves the performance. And the way it works is like, okay, model parallelism has
성능이 크게 향상됩니다. 작동 방식은 다음과 같습니다. 모델 병렬성은
the largest communication overhead. So we prioritize placing the model parallel groups within a note
가장 큰 통신 오버헤드. 따라서 우리는 노트 내에 모델 병렬 그룹을 배치하는 것을 우선시합니다.
to utilize the larger inter-node bandwidth. Then we have Megatron LM for tensor slicing that is
더 큰 노드 간 대역폭을 활용합니다. 그런 다음 텐서 슬라이싱을 위한 Megatron LM이 있습니다.
happening inside here. And just exactly as I described, then we do the pipeline stages inside.
여기 안에서 일어나고 있어요. 제가 설명한 것과 똑같이 내부에서 파이프라인 단계를 수행합니다.
Yeah, and then we see that with zero, we basically combine all the benefits for all the approaches
예, 그리고 0을 사용하면 기본적으로 모든 접근 방식의 모든 이점을 결합합니다.
that we talked about, we get more than a trillium parameter model, we can do it, we can do parallelism
우리가 얘기했던 것처럼, 우리는 Trillium 매개변수 모델 이상의 것을 얻을 수 있습니다. 우리는 그것을 할 수 있고, 병렬화를 할 수 있습니다.
to more than 1000x, we have very good compute efficiency. And the very good thing about zero is
1000x 이상으로 계산 효율성이 매우 좋습니다. 그리고 제로의 가장 좋은 점은
that you really don't need to rewrite the code, because it is just an optimizer that you can
코드를 다시 작성할 필요가 없습니다. 왜냐하면 이는 단지 최적화 도구일 뿐이기 때문입니다.
apply in PyTorch. You can just use the deep speed library to do it for you. Yeah, and then you can
PyTorch에 적용해보세요. 당신은 단지 당신을 위해 그것을 할 수 있는 깊은 속도 라이브러리를 사용할 수 있습니다. 응, 그럼 넌 할 수 있어
see that you really need 3D parallelism in order to do stuff on the GPT3 scale. So for, for example,
GPT3 규모의 작업을 수행하려면 3D 병렬성이 실제로 필요하다는 것을 확인하십시오. 예를 들어,
if you're doing model parallel equal one, there's literally no way you can get any performance on a
모델 병렬을 1로 동일하게 수행하는 경우 문자 그대로 성능을 얻을 수 있는 방법이 없습니다.
GPT3 scale, you need at least model parallel equals two with very high pipeline parallel or and so
GPT3 규모, 최소한 모델 병렬이 2와 같고 매우 높은 파이프라인 병렬이 필요합니다.
on. You get the best kind of 3D parallelism is when the pipeline parallel is 20, model parallel is
에. 파이프라인 병렬이 20이고 모델 병렬이 20일 때 가장 좋은 3D 병렬성을 얻을 수 있습니다.
two, and the data parallel is 20. The idea is that model parallel needs to be low for very high
2이고 데이터 병렬은 20입니다. 아이디어는 모델 병렬이 매우 높을수록 낮아야 한다는 것입니다.
performance, because it's only used for memory efficiency, it's not used for performance gains,
성능은 메모리 효율성을 위해서만 사용되기 때문에 성능 향상을 위해 사용되지는 않습니다.
because it's not very efficient performance wise if we're talking, because of the communication
왜냐하면 우리가 이야기하고 있는 것은 성능 측면에서 매우 효율적이지 않기 때문입니다. 의사소통 때문에
overhead that it introduces. Yep, so do you saw my references? Thank you for listening, and I hope
그것이 도입하는 오버헤드. 응, 내 참고자료 봤어? 들어주셔서 감사합니다.
this was useful to you.
이것은 당신에게 유용했습니다.